<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

   <statements version="7.0.0" htmlParse="false">
     <statement id="1">Pharmacists investing in medication management services is aligned with a broader vision for pharmacy.</statement>
     <statement id="2">Pharmacy has sufficient capacity (cost of resources, staffing levels, training).</statement>
     <statement id="3">Patients expect us to deliver this health service.</statement>
     <statement id="4">It is important to communicate with staff well and work as a team when implementing the service.</statement>
     <statement id="5">Pharmacy is eligible to participate in the Community Pharmacy Agreement (Government funded program).</statement>
     <statement id="6">Community pharmacies need to shift to a health solution-oriented service position if they want to remain relevant and viable.</statement>
     <statement id="7">Professional services contribute to increasing the pharmacy&apos;s gross profit.</statement>
     <statement id="8">Most health services have been done before, somewhere in the country, at this point.</statement>
     <statement id="9">We reward certain team members for their dedication to a particular health service trying to help them feel not only personal satisfaction, but financial satisfaction from taking on an extra responsibility.</statement>
     <statement id="10">In our pharmacy, we use the personality profile assessments.</statement>
     <statement id="11">Recognising that some people love to be in the dispensary and nothing more,  they love that task completion over and over and over again, very quick reward.</statement>
     <statement id="12">The public is learning more that we aren&apos;t free, that we are a health professional too.</statement>
     <statement id="13">You are devaluing the service if you are not dedicating enough time to it and attaching the corresponding cost to that.</statement>
     <statement id="14">We do evaluate team-wise in terms of, for example, performance reviews. We&apos;ll ask questions like “what&apos;s working well in the pharmacy”, or “what&apos;s your favourite thing”, “what&apos;s your favourite service to do”, “what&apos;s your least favourite service to do”, “how can we do better”? So not quantitative as much as qualitative kind of gut feel thing and there&apos;s ongoing conversations every day.</statement>
     <statement id="15">We&apos;ve always done evaluation surveys in the pharmacy.</statement>
     <statement id="16">Increasingly there&apos;s a public expectation that no matter where you consume anything really, that you have the opportunity to give feedback.</statement>
     <statement id="17">Do we have the allocated pharmacist to be able to provide this service?</statement>
     <statement id="18">So whether or not we&apos;re prescribing antibiotics for urinary tract infections  or whatever, we’ve got the support of the the pharmacy professional bodies and everyone that&apos;s providing those services for us to be able to do that.</statement>
     <statement id="19">I think it just takes one pharmacist, or someone just really having that particular interest and willing to lead that, for it to be effective as well.</statement>
     <statement id="20">You need that team leader, and that could be nominated by the employer.</statement>
     <statement id="21">So knowing the true statistics is why in the 1st place you&apos;d do the professional service.</statement>
     <statement id="22">I think evaluation is very powerful in itself and gives us the confidence to charge a fee for service.</statement>
     <statement id="23">It was not just providing the consultation. Actually saying that the new service includes a consultation, but also includes a one week follow-up, a four week follow-up, ongoing support and service, and also a referral letter to the doctor.</statement>
     <statement id="24">Talking to other pharmacists, pharmacists around our country, that are starting to do it in, for instance, wound care, in men&apos;s health that sort of gives you a bit more confidence seeing others that have started to do it as well.</statement>
     <statement id="25">I don&apos;t think what other pharmacies are doing regarding professional services influences ours that much.</statement>
     <statement id="26">And so the prospect becomes not of what&apos;s the price, but what&apos;s the value.</statement>
     <statement id="27">We try and build the delivery of professional services as a desirable thing. It&apos;s not everybody&apos;s cup of tea, but the vast majority of the team members that I have worked with are kind of hungry for that kind of responsibility.</statement>
     <statement id="28">People in pharmacy tend to be one of two major personality types: 1. people-focused, engaged, people serving and chatting and building rapport. And 2. &apos;back of house&apos; people - checking packs efficiently and thoroughly, compounding, on the computer. People that are better for professional services roles tend to be the first ones.</statement>
     <statement id="29">We want to align our services with what the market and other health professionals want, because that goes to what&apos;s going to be successful and what won&apos;t.</statement>
     <statement id="30">The only people really that I&apos;d want to see to that [blood cholesterol health check] service are the people that are saying: “I&apos;m not going to see my doctor. There&apos;s just no way I&apos;m doing that. It&apos;s either the pharmacy convenience or it&apos;s nothing.” And to those people, I&apos;ll say: “Well, OK, I can maybe motivate you through doing some of the..”</statement>
     <statement id="31">Professional satisfaction is probably a massive part of what drives us to do professional services in community pharmacy.</statement>
     <statement id="32">This is great. Like, I&apos;m helping people. People are coming in. They&apos;re sad, they&apos;re upset, they&apos;re hurt, they’re distressed. But they&apos;re leaving here with a solution, like I&apos;ve done something worthwhile.</statement>
     <statement id="33">If I&apos;m not going to do COVID-19 vaccinations, then who else can I expect to do it? So it just felt like if I was not gonna do it, I was effectively dooming these people to not be able to receive the service. And I couldn&apos;t in good conscience do that.</statement>
     <statement id="34">Then I better do the vaccinating. It would be so hypocritical to expect the benefits, but not be part of the solution.</statement>
     <statement id="35">I try to look at the person as a whole, not just as the medication that they&apos;re on. So it all sort of started blending together. And you know, we have such a range of services that we offer in the pharmacy.</statement>
     <statement id="36">I&apos;m not just the pharmacist. If I&apos;m just the authority figure, then it&apos;s like I&apos;m removing myself from the community in a certain way. And they&apos;re not as comfortable to express their personal issues to me, and that&apos;s the same I think with everybody that I work with.</statement>
     <statement id="37">We really haven&apos;t had very high staff turnover. Everyone who&apos;s been with us has been with us for years.</statement>
     <statement id="38">I think that when people give us a comment, we tend to take that on board straight away.</statement>
     <statement id="39">So if they feel that they&apos;re going to be better served by a discount pharmacy, there is a legit market for that. There&apos;s people for whom that best suits them. Let them go there. They&apos;re not the people that I&apos;m after anyway. Because it is such a low-income area, there are 3 discount pharmacies within 10-minutes. We&apos;re not affected by them.</statement>
     <statement id="40">My pricing - so I can see what they&apos;re charging as well, you know, so I&apos;m going well, a different pharmacy in a  slightly more well-off area is charging $10.00 for a blood pressure test. Now, you know, we’re in this area where it&apos;s rougher. So I&apos;m going to charge $5.</statement>
     <statement id="41">So I&apos;m trying to keep the charges minimal as possible, but blood sugar testing to me is more of a luxury service, because you&apos;re getting the national diabetes service subsidy already. You know, a lot of our people, the blood sugar machines, are free of charge.</statement>
     <statement id="42">People can go and get the vaccines funded by government at the doctor. Totally free of charge, you know? So I&apos;m like, well, the vaccine is free, you know, these are older people. They have the option to go and get it done somewhere else free. So we&apos;re starting at $15 if they want to pay for the convenience.</statement>
     <statement id="43">In our pharmacy we&apos;ve got a great range of ages, experience levels and basically it&apos;s a great amalgamation of the team that we have.</statement>
     <statement id="44">The impact of TV and social media is driving our patients to come to us and ask questions. So it kind of prompts us to, you know, be aware of everything that&apos;s happening.</statement>
     <statement id="45">Basically none of the procedures I&apos;ve ever written have now been edited by the staff. So with that, we do have feedback because that line of communication is so free and and the environment we have in the store is very friendly.</statement>
     <statement id="46">It&apos;s more like: Can we do it better than they can? And that&apos;s where we weigh it up as to whether we put up our hand to deliver this service, or not.</statement>
     <statement id="47">Space was an enabler for professional services in our pharmacy. When I first started there we weren&apos;t delivering vaccinations because we didn&apos;t have the space. But we changed an old storage room into a vaccine room because it was big enough and there was enough light and everything like that.</statement>
     <statement id="48">Although it may not seem like much, but in the last year or so, I&apos;ve personally delivered over 1000 COVID-19 vaccines. Without that it&apos;s 1000 less vaccines delivered to our community or 1000 more that would have put so much pressure on the other pharmacies around us.</statement>
     <statement id="49">And we have a bit of a a health focused calendar across the group. So we&apos;ll try and align the topic. So it does affect the schedule sometimes. We might have something we&apos;ve been working on, but we kind of have to wait until that topic is coming up in the pharmacy because you&apos;ll have better impact. You&apos;ll have a better result.</statement>
     <statement id="50">I&apos;d say delivery of professional services has always been &apos;ad hoc&apos; and random, and only more recently we&apos;re we&apos;re getting better with our internal processes and how we do that more systematically and it&apos;s easier.</statement>
     <statement id="51">The fact is, you know, if you have to order in equipment, if you have to have specialised equipment, it&apos;s it&apos;s a huge factor for commencing that particular professional service in community pharmacy.</statement>
     <statement id="52">I think it&apos;s a race to the bottom, if we&apos;re all competing with each other on service pricing.</statement>
     <statement id="53">We had all these different services, but none of them were actually taking off back then, because we had diabetes services, weight management and everything like that. And then we had the big piece of paper, and we were trying to target what does this community, our community actually need? And is this viable to run with our team, with our skills and with our trainings?</statement>
     <statement id="54">We do have our formal team meetings, which usually happen every three to six months, depending on what&apos;s going on. Like right now, we&apos;re doing it monthly.</statement>
     <statement id="55">I think it&apos;s because we have built up a bit of a reputation and then they know they can trust us and also having that connection, we have some patients referred to us from the local hospitals and we also try to have those discussions with our patients in store as well.</statement>
     <statement id="56">We also do have some partnerships between our pharmacy and disability homes in the area.</statement>
     <statement id="57">We do tend to prefer to have the evidence beforehand, but we are actually part of a few trials, like pilots as well, so we&apos;re happy to do that and be kind of the &apos;guinea pig&apos; to find out if it does actually work in community pharmacies.</statement>
     <statement id="58">We do have that - evaluation. So it&apos;s kind of optional for our patients, but for each of the services, there&apos;s like a kind of tick like how they felt about the service and then a little comment section as well and any improvements and things. So that&apos;s where we&apos;ve got some feedback.</statement>
     <statement id="59">Our pharmacists, they&apos;re better at a service because sometimes it just depends on their passion. I would say that passion is probably the biggest driver in our pharmacy.</statement>
     <statement id="60">Basically at the start of this year myself and 2 of our pharmacists, we actually sat down and thought we&apos;re trying to think of the new service we&apos;re going to implement. Then we kind of all brainstorm and run it all down. And then we came together and discussed.</statement>
     <statement id="61">Timing is very crucial because sometimes the team can feel quite overwhelmed so you&apos;re not really having too many changes at once.</statement>
     <statement id="62">The staff culture, having the staff who understands the value of services to the pharmacy is very important.</statement>
     <statement id="63">Everything I&apos;m doing, my vision is to try improve this service so the whole community of pharmacists can benefit from it.</statement>
   </statements>
   